<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
]>
<section>
	<title>מוסכמות לתיעוד</title>
	 <para>
		מדריך זה משתמש במספר מוסכמות לצורך הדגשת חלק מהמילים והמשפטים ובכדי להסב את תשומת הלב לפרטי מידע מסוימים.
	</para>
	 <para>
		בגרסאות המסמך המודפסות או השמורות בפורמט PDF, המדריך משתמש בגופנים הנלקחים מתוך <ulink url="https://fedorahosted.org/liberation-fonts/">Liberation Fonts</ulink>. אם גופנים אלו מותקנים במערכת, אזי גם גרסת ה-HTML משתמשת בהם לתצוגה. במידה ואין הדבר כך, המסמך מוצג בגופנים שקולים אחרים. הערה: גופני Liberation Fonts כלולים כברירת מחדל במערכת Red Hat Enterprise Linux מגרסה 5 והלאה.
	</para>
	 <section>
		<title>מוסכמות טיפוגרפיות</title>
		 <para>
			ארבע מוסכמות טיפוגרפיות משמשות למשיכת תשומת הלב למילים ומשפטים מסוימים. להלן המוסכמות ונסיבות השימוש בהן.
		</para>
		 <para>
			<literal>Mono-spaced Bold</literal>
		</para>
		 <para>
			Used to highlight system input, including shell commands, file names and paths. Also used to highlight keycaps and key combinations. For example:
		</para>
		 <blockquote>
			<para>
				להצגת תוכן הקובץ <filename>my_next_bestselling_novel</filename> בתיקיה הנוכחית יש להקליד את הפקודה <command>cat my_next_bestselling_novel</command> בשורת הפקודה ולהקיש על מקש <keycap>Enter</keycap> לצורך הפעלתה.
			</para>

		</blockquote>
		 <para>
			The above includes a file name, a shell command and a keycap, all presented in mono-spaced bold and all distinguishable thanks to context.
		</para>
		 <para>
			Key combinations can be distinguished from keycaps by the hyphen connecting each part of a key combination. For example:
		</para>
		 <blockquote>
			<para>
				יש להקיש <keycap>Enter</keycap> לביצוע הפקודה.
			</para>
			 <para>
				יש להקיש <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>F1</keycap></keycombo> כדי לעבור למסוף הווירטואלי הראשון. נא להקיש <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>F7</keycap></keycombo> לצורך חזרה לסביבת העבודה הגרפית.
			</para>

		</blockquote>
		 <para>
			The first paragraph highlights the particular keycap to press. The second highlights two key combinations (each a set of three keycaps with each set pressed simultaneously).
		</para>
		 <para>
			If source code is discussed, class names, methods, functions, variable names and returned values mentioned within a paragraph will be presented as above, in <literal>mono-spaced bold</literal>. For example:
		</para>
		 <blockquote>
			<para>
				מחלקות קשורות לקבצים כוללות <classname>filesystem</classname> עבור מערכות קבצים, <classname>file</classname> עבור קבצים וכן <classname>dir</classname> עבור תיקיות. לכל מחלקה משויך אוסף הרשאות משלה.
			</para>

		</blockquote>
		 <para>
			<application>Proportional Bold</application>
		</para>
		 <para>
			This denotes words or phrases encountered on a system, including application names; dialog box text; labeled buttons; check-box and radio button labels; menu titles and sub-menu titles. For example:
		</para>
		 <blockquote>
			<para>
				Choose <menuchoice><guimenu>System</guimenu><guisubmenu>Preferences</guisubmenu><guimenuitem>Mouse</guimenuitem></menuchoice> from the main menu bar to launch <application>Mouse Preferences</application>. In the <guilabel>Buttons</guilabel> tab, click the <guilabel>Left-handed mouse</guilabel> check box and click <guibutton>Close</guibutton> to switch the primary mouse button from the left to the right (making the mouse suitable for use in the left hand).
			</para>
			 <para>
				To insert a special character into a <application>gedit</application> file, choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Applications</guimenu><guisubmenu>Accessories</guisubmenu><guimenuitem>Character Map</guimenuitem></menuchoice> from the main menu bar. Next, choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Search</guimenu><guimenuitem>Find&hellip;</guimenuitem></menuchoice> from the <application>Character Map</application> menu bar, type the name of the character in the <guilabel>Search</guilabel> field and click <guibutton>Next</guibutton>. The character you sought will be highlighted in the <guilabel>Character Table</guilabel>. Double-click this highlighted character to place it in the <guilabel>Text to copy</guilabel> field and then click the <guibutton>Copy</guibutton> button. Now switch back to your document and choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Paste</guimenuitem></menuchoice> from the <application>gedit</application> menu bar.
			</para>

		</blockquote>
		 <para>
			The above text includes application names; system-wide menu names and items; application-specific menu names; and buttons and text found within a GUI interface, all presented in proportional bold and all distinguishable by context.
		</para>
		 <para>
			<command><replaceable>ריווח שווה מודגש ומוטה</replaceable></command> או <application><replaceable>ריווח יחסי מודגש ומוטה</replaceable></application>
		</para>
		 <para>
			Whether mono-spaced bold or proportional bold, the addition of italics indicates replaceable or variable text. Italics denotes text you do not input literally or displayed text that changes depending on circumstance. For example:
		</para>
		 <blockquote>
			<para>
				בכדי להתחבר למחשב מרוחק בעזרת ssh יש להקליד בשורת הפקודה <command>ssh <replaceable>username</replaceable>@<replaceable>domain.name</replaceable></command>. אם שם המחשב המרוחק הוא <filename>example.com</filename> ושם המשתמש על המחשב הזה הוא john אז צריך להקליד <command>ssh john@example.com</command>.
			</para>
			 <para>
				הפקודה <command>mount -o remount <replaceable>file-system</replaceable></command> מעגנת מחדש את מערכת הקבצים שצוינה. לדוגמה, כדי לעגן מחדש את מערכת הקבצים <filename>/home</filename>, הפקודה הנדרשת היא <command>mount -o remount /home</command>.
			</para>
			 <para>
				כדי לראות את הגרסה של חבילת תכנה מותקנת, יש להריץ את הפקודה <command>rpm -q <replaceable>package</replaceable></command>. יתקבל פלט במבנה: <command><replaceable>package-version-release</replaceable></command>.
			</para>

		</blockquote>
		 <para>
			שימו לב למילים המודגשות והמוטות לעיל &mdash; username, domain.name, file-system, package, version ו-release. כל מילה כזו מציינת מקום של טקסט שיוקלד או שיוצג על ידי המערכת.
		</para>
		 <para>
			מלבד השימוש המקובל לכותרת של עבודה, אותיות מוטות מסמנות גם את השימוש הראשון במושג חדש חשוב. לדוגמה:
		</para>
		 <blockquote>
			<para>
				Publican is a <firstterm>DocBook</firstterm> publishing system.
			</para>

		</blockquote>

	</section>
	
	 <section>
		<title>מוסכמות לגבי ציטטות</title>
		 <para>
			Terminal output and source code listings are set off visually from the surrounding text.
		</para>
		 <para>
			Output sent to a terminal is set in <computeroutput>mono-spaced roman</computeroutput> and presented thus:
		</para>
		 
<screen>books        Desktop   documentation  drafts  mss    photos   stuff  svn
books_tests  Desktop1  downloads      images  notes  scripts  svgs</screen>
		 <para>
			Source-code listings are also set in <computeroutput>mono-spaced roman</computeroutput> but add syntax highlighting as follows:
		</para>
		 
<programlisting language="Java">package org.jboss.book.jca.ex1;

import javax.naming.InitialContext;

public class ExClient
{
   public static void main(String args[]) 
       throws Exception
   {
      InitialContext iniCtx = new InitialContext();
      Object         ref    = iniCtx.lookup(&#34;EchoBean&#34;);
      EchoHome       home   = (EchoHome) ref;
      Echo           echo   = home.create();

      System.out.println(&#34;Created Echo&#34;);

      System.out.println(&#34;Echo.echo(&#39;Hello&#39;) = &#34; + echo.echo(&#34;Hello&#34;));
   }
}</programlisting>

	</section>
	
	 <section>
		<title>הערות ואזהרות</title>
		 <para>
			לבסוף, אנו משתמשים בשלושה סימנים חזותיים לצורך הסבת תשומת הלב למידע חשוב.
		</para>
		 <note>
			<title>הערה</title>
			 <para>
				Notes are tips, shortcuts or alternative approaches to the task at hand. Ignoring a note should have no negative consequences, but you might miss out on a trick that makes your life easier.
			</para>

		</note>
		 <important>
			<title>שימו לב</title>
			 <para>
				Important boxes detail things that are easily missed: configuration changes that only apply to the current session, or services that need restarting before an update will apply. Ignoring a box labeled &#39;Important&#39; won&#39;t cause data loss but may cause irritation and frustration.
			</para>

		</important>
		 <warning>
			<title>אזהרה</title>
			 <para>
				Warnings should not be ignored. Ignoring warnings will most likely cause data loss.
			</para>

		</warning>

	</section>

</section>


